Guide to the J. E. Wallace Sterling, President of Stanford University, Papers
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
J. E. Wallace Sterling, president of Stanford University, papers
1913-1969
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Sterling, J. E. Wallace (John Ewart Wallace)
SC0216
300 Linear Feet
Papers primarily represent Sterling's years as President of Stanford University and include correspondence, memoranda, proposals, speeches, minutes, reports, budgets, clippings, and legal papers.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography
J.E. Wallace Sterling, president of Stanford University from 1949-1968, earned his A.B. in history at the University of Toronto in 1927; he taught at the University of Alberta while pursuing graduate work there from 1928-1930. He came to Stanford in 1930 to pursue his doctorate, which he received in 1938. While at Stanford, he was also a research assistant in the Hoover Library and taught in the History Department. From 1938 to 1948 Sterling taught at the California Institute of Technology, where he was elected chairman of the faculty in 1944. He had been Director of the Huntington Library and Art Gallery for five months when he accepted the presidency of Stanford University. During Sterling's 19 years as president, Stanford's endowment nearly doubled, the faculty increased by 170 percent, graduate programs were improved, major building plans were completed, the Medical School was moved to campus from San Francisco, and the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center was built. After his retirement in 1968, Sterling was named University Chancellor. He died on July 1, 1985.
Scope and Content of Collection
These records primarily represent Sterling's years as President of Stanford University and include correspondence, memoranda, proposals, speeches, minutes, reports, budgets, clippings, and legal papers. Some files predate his term as president. There is a separate series pertaining to the Hoover Institution, 1948-68. Collection also includes Sterling's class notes, lectures, manuscripts, and professional correspondence, 1925-1949.
Arrangement note
Materials are arranged as received.
Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Sterling, J. E. Wallace (John Ewart Wallace); Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace
- Papers, Series 1
  - Air Science and Tactics, Dept. of, 1950-1956 (Box 1.1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    correspondence contains the following 5 misfiled items at front: Assoc. of World Language; Allen & Company; Antonelli, Muriel; American Meteorological Society; Anderson, Walker E.; Art and Architecture - budget
  - Air Science and Tactics, Dept. of, 1952-1955 (Box 1.1, Folder 2)
    correspondence
  - Air Science and Tactics, Dept. of, 1956-1962 (Box 1.1, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology (Box 1.2, Folder 4)
  - Art and Architecture, Dept. of, 1946-1950 (Box 1.2, Folder 5)
  - Art and Architecture, Dept. of, 1954 (Box 1.2, Folder 6)
    one letter about improving lecture halls for slides
  - Art and Architecture, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 1.2, Folder 7)
    budget memos
  - Asian Languages (formerly Dept. of Asiatic and Slavic Studies), 1956-1961 (Box 1.2, Folder 8)
    contains Slavic Studies
  - Biological Sciences, Dept. of, 1948-1952 (Box 1.2, Folder 9)
  - Biological Sciences, Dept. of, 1954-1956 (Box 1.2, Folder 10)
  - Biological Sciences, Dept. of, 1952-1956 (Box 1.2, Folder 11)
  - Biological Sciences, Dept. of, 1956-1964 (Box 1.3, Folder 12)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 1.3, Folder 13)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1949-1950 (Box 1.3, Folder 14)
    contains Luthy, Nydia resignation during Justice Dept. communism hunt
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1951 (Box 1.3, Folder 15)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 1.3, Folder 16)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 1.3, Folder 17)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 1.3, Folder 18)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 1.3, Folder 19)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 1.3, Folder 20)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1955-1964 (Box 1.4, Folder 21)
  - Classics, Dept. of, 1946-1955 (Box 1.4, Folder 22)
  - Classics, Dept. of, 1956-1963 (Box 1.4, Folder 23)
  - Communication and Journalism, Dept. of, 1957-1962 (Box 1.5, Folder 24)
  - Communication and Journalism, Dept. of, 1962-1964 (Box 1.5, Folder 25)
  - Computer Science, Dept. of, 1964 (Box 1.5, Folder 26)
    Request to transform division into dept.
  - Computation Center, 1961-1964 (Box 1.5, Folder 27)
  - Earth Sciences, School of (formerly School of Mineral Sciences), 1961-1964 (Box 1.5, Folder 28)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 2.6, Folder 1)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1949-1950 (Box 2.6, Folder 2)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 2.6, Folder 3)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 2.6, Folder 4)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1953-1955 (Box 2.6, Folder 5)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1956-1959 (Box 2.6, Folder 6)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1958-1964 (Box 2.6, Folder 7)
  - Economics, Dept. of, 1959-1964 (Box 2.6, Folder 8)
  - English, Dept. of, 1947-1949 (Box 2.6, Folder 9)
  - English, Dept. of, 1949-1951 (Box 2.7, Folder 10)
  - English, Dept. of, 1950-1954 (Box 2.7, Folder 11)
  - English, Dept. of, 1953-1955 (Box 2.7, Folder 12)
  - English, Dept. of, 1955-1957 (Box 2.7, Folder 13)
  - Humanities and Sciences, School of, 1965 (Box 2.7, Folder 14)
    faculty salary surveys
  - English, Dept. of, 1957-1959 (Box 2.7, Folder 15)
  - English, Dept. of, 1959-1964 (Box 2.7, Folder 16)
  - Geography, Dept. of, 1948-1957 (Box 2.8, Folder 17)
  - Geography, Dept. of, 1957-1963 (Box 2.8, Folder 18)
  - Geology, Dept. of, 1946-1950 (Box 2.8, Folder 19)
  - Geology, Dept. of, 1958-1960 (Box 2.8, Folder 20)
  - Germanic Languages, Dept. of, 1947-1951 (Box 2.8, Folder 21)
  - Germanic and Romanic Languages, Dept. of, 1950-1953 (Box 2.9, Folder 22)
  - Germanic and Romanic Languages, Dept. of, 1953-1957 (Box 2.9, Folder 23)
  - Germanic and Romanic Languages, Dept. of, 1956-1958 (Box 2.9, Folder 24)
  - History, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 2.9, Folder 25)
  - History, Dept. of, 1949-1951 (Box 2.9, Folder 26)
  - History, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 3.1, Folder 1)
  - History, Dept. of, 1953-1957 (Box 3.1, Folder 2)
  - History, Dept. of, 1956-1958 (Box 3.1, Folder 3)
  - History, Dept. of, 1958-1962 (Box 3.1, Folder 4)
  - Journalism, Div. of, 1944-1955 (Box 3.2, Folder 5)
    Name changes from Division of Journalism to Institute for Journalistic Studies to Dept. of Communication and Journalism (1955). Within this Dept. is the Institute for Communication Research.
  - Journalistic Studies, Instutite of, 1949-1954 (Box 3.2, Folder 6)
  - Communication and Journalism, Dept. of, 1955-1957 (Box 3.2, Folder 7)
  - Mathematics, Dept. of, 1945-1953 (Box 3.2, Folder 8)
  - Mathematics, Dept. of, 1955 (Box 3.2, Folder 9)
    contains Browder, Felix appointment appeal (denied for public and government relations reasons)
  - Mathematics, Dept. of, 1957-1958 (Box 3.2, Folder 10)
  - Mathematics, Dept. of, 1959-1966 (Box 3.2, Folder 11)
  - Military Science and Tactics (ROTC), Dept. of, 1952-1955 (Box 3.2, Folder 12)
  - Military Science and Tactics (ROTC), Dept. of, 1952-1959 (Box 3.2, Folder 13)
  - Military Science and Tactics (ROTC), Dept. of, 1952-1962 (Box 3.3, Folder 14)
  - Military Science and Tactics (ROTC), Dept. of, 1962-1964 (Box 3.3, Folder 15)
  - Military Science and Tactics (ROTC), Dept. of, 1962-1964 (Box 3.3, Folder 16)
    Distinguished Military Student appointments
  - Modern European Languages, Dept. of, 1959-1962 (Box 3.3, Folder 17)
  - Music, Dept. of, 1952-1954 (Box 3.3, Folder 18)
    Contains 1952 proposal for new music building next to Memorial Auditorium (with plans)
  - Music, Dept. of, 1956-1958 (Box 3.4, Folder 19)
  - Music, Dept. of, 1958-1964 (Box 3.4, Folder 20)
  - Music, Dept. of, 1950 (Box 3.4, Folder 21)
  - Music, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 3.4, Folder 22)
  - Music, Dept. of, 1951-1954 (Box 3.4, Folder 23)
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1950-1951 (Box 3.4, Folder 24)
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1951-1952 (Box 3.4, Folder 25)
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1953-1954 (Box 3.4, Folder 26)
    Also called Dept. of Naval Science and Tactics
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1953-1954 (Box 3.4, Folder 27)
    faculty appointments and nominations
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Naval Science (NROTC), 1951-1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, 1953-1964 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1944-1958 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Referred to as Dept. of Physical Education and Athletics
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Football coach Marchie Schwartz (contract renewal -- letters pro and con)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    President's Courtesy Football Ticket List
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Big Game 1956
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Football Awards Banquet
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Big Game 1957
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    President's Football Ticket Courtesy List
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Beer Sponsorships
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Rose Bowl Courtesy Tickets
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1958-1965 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Big Game 1960
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Football Ticket distribution
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Football luncheons, reunions
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Big Game Week
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Football Coach search
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Jack Curtice, football coaching contract not renewed
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    President's Football Courtesy Tickets
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Lowell Wilson football injury
  - Athletics and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Football Tickets
  - Physical Education for Women, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Physical Education for Women, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Physical Education for Women, Dept. of, 1952-1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Physical Sciences, Dept. of, 1953-1958 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1952-1957 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Physics, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    budget
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1952-1957 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    some material on Sibley
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    Professor Mulford Q. Sibley (appointment denied, mail pro and con)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Sibley, Mulford (appointment deliberations)
  - Political Science, Dept. of, 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Romanic Languages, Dept. of, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Discussion of Hispanic American program
  - Romanic Languages, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Romanic Languages, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Department is separated in Fall 1956
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Sociology, Dept. of, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Sociology, Dept. of, 1959-1964 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Speech and Drama, Dept. of, 1960-1962 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Statistics, Dept. of, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Statistics, Dept. of, 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Statistics, Dept. of, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Statistics, Dept. of, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Statistics, Dept. of, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Statistics, Dept. of, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - General "A", 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    correspondence with associations, councils, individuals, etc.
  - General "A", 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - General "A", 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - General "A", 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General "A", 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General "A", 1956 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Academic Council, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    notes for remarks about staff reorganization
  - Academic Council, 1949-1953 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    President's reports to the council
  - Accreditation, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Admissions (A-M), 1949 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Admissions (N-Z), 1949 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Admissions (A-M), 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Admissions (N-Z), 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Admissions, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Admissions, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Admissions, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Admissions, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Admissions, 1956-1959 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Admissions, 1959-1962 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Advisory Board, 1945-1951 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Air Science and Tactics, Dept. of, 1946-1950 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Air Force, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    Air Academy
  - Air Force Academy Site Selection Board, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Air Travel Reservations, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    Faculty's travel reservations made through the President's Office
  - Air University, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Alumni, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Alumni, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Alumni Association, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Association, 1943, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Association, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Association, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Association, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Association, Campus Liaison Committee, 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Clubs, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Conference, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Alumni Conference, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Alumni Conference, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Conference, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Conference, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Alumni Conference, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Alumni Conference, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Fresno-Bakersfield speech
  - Alumni Conference, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    Phoenix speech
  - Alumni Conference, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    Santa Barbara speech
  - Alumni Deceased, 1940-1951 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Alumni Association, 1950-1952 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Building of Bowman Alumni House
  - Alumni Association, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Alumni Association Reunions, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Alumni Association - Alumni Review, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Alumni Association - Alumni Review, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    Name changes to Stanford Review
  - American Academy of Asian Studies, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    Sterling was a member of the Advisory Board
  - American Academy of Asian Studies, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - American Academy of Asian Studies, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - American Academy of Asian Studies, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1951 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1952 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1955 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP) (Box 8, Folder 36)
    History of AAUP - Academic Freedom and Tenure
  - American Association of University Women (AAUW), 1952 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - American Association of University Women (AAUW), 1953 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - American Association of University Women (AAUW), 1955 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), 1950-1953 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), 1955 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - American Institute of Pacific Relations (AIPR), 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - American Institute of Pacific Relations (AIPR), 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Sterling resigned from board in Feb. 1954
  - American Institute of Pacific Relations (AIPR), 1955 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - American Red Cross, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Red Cross fund raising appeal
  - American Round Table, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - American Studies, Program in, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    contains "American Ideals Series" publication info
  - American Universities Field Staff, 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Paged by Don Carlson, Univ. Relations 3/5/77
  - American Universities Field Staff, 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - American Universities Field Staff, 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Annual Report, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Not published from 1946-?
  - Annual Reviews, Inc., 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Publishers of scientific reviews. Based at Stanford until late 1956.
  - Annual Reviews, Inc., 1956 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Applications for Positions (A-M), 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Applications for Positions (N-Z), 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Applied Mathematics and Statistics Laboratory, 1951-1955 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Applied Mathematics and Statistics Laboratory, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Arctic Research Laboratory, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Proposed contract with Office of Naval Research to run lab
  - Arctic Research Laboratory, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Arctic Research Laboratory, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    Contains photographs of Point Barrow facility and staff
  - Armory, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Army, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Army, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Army, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Military Science and Tactics (ROTC), Dept. of, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Arnautoff, Victor, 1955-1957 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    Art Professor retained despite allegations of communism. Sterling: "No proven communist should hold a position on our faculty."
  - Art Gallery and Museum, 1945-1956 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Art Gallery and Museum, 1956-1962 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Art Gallery and Museum, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    Lost paintings belonging to Mr. Arthur Brown, Jr.
  - Asiatic and Slavic Studies, Dept. of, 1946-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Reports from various departments on establishing a program
  - Asiatic and Slavic Studies, Dept. of, 1948-1956 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    see also Asian Languages, Dept. of